<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>All Posts - Cyberspace Operations</title>
        <link>https://cyberoperationer.github.io/posts/</link>
        <description>All Posts | Cyberspace Operations</description>
        <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><managingEditor>g.huskaj@gcsp.ch (CO)</managingEditor>
            <webMaster>g.huskaj@gcsp.ch (CO)</webMaster><lastBuildDate>Mon, 20 Mar 2023 00:51:25 &#43;0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cyberoperationer.github.io/posts/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" /><item>
    <title>TikTok banned on Government Electronic Devices</title>
    <link>https://cyberoperationer.github.io/2023/tiktok-banned-on-government-electronic-devices/</link>
    <pubDate>Mon, 20 Mar 2023 00:51:25 &#43;0100</pubDate>
    <author>CO</author>
    <guid>https://cyberoperationer.github.io/2023/tiktok-banned-on-government-electronic-devices/</guid>
    <description><![CDATA[<h1 id="on-16-march-2023-the-uk-cabinet-office-announced-that-the-social-media-app-tiktok-is-banned-on-government-electronic-deviceshttpswwwgovukgovernmentnewstiktok-banned-on-uk-government-devices-as-part-of-wider-app-review-the-reason"><a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/tiktok-banned-on-uk-government-devices-as-part-of-wider-app-review" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer ">On 16 March 2023, the U.K. Cabinet Office announced that the social media app TikTok is banned on government electronic devices</a>. The reason?</h1>
<h3 id="a-security-review-ordered-by-the-cabinet-office-ministers-aimed-to-look-at-the-potential-vulnerability-of-government-data-from-social-media-apps-on-devices-and-risks-around-how-sensitive-information-could-be-accessed-and-used-by-some-platforms">A security review ordered by the Cabinet Office Ministers aimed to look “at the potential vulnerability of government data from social media apps on devices and risks around how sensitive information could be accessed and used by some platforms.”</h3>
<p><a href="https://www.euronews.com/next/2023/03/17/which-countries-have-banned-tiktok-cybersecurity-data-privacy-espionage-fears" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer ">Euronews</a> reported on 17 March 2023 that in addition to the U.K., “New Zealand, The European Parliament, European Commission, and the E.U. Council,…, Belgium, Canada, Denmark, India, Taiwan, and the United States” have banned TikTok from government devices. Euronews reports that Afghanistan and Pakistan have also banned the app.</p>
<p>Their concerns are warranted.</p>
<p>On 4 July 2022, <a href="https://internet2-0.com/technical-analysis-of-tiktok-app/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer ">internet2.0</a> presented the “Technical Analysis of TikTok App.” Their media release provided a link to <a href="https://penetrum.com/tiktok/Penetrum_TikTok_Security_Analysis_whitepaper.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer ">Penetrum</a>, who conducted a Security Analysis on TikTok. Security Analysis is a process of identifying vulnerabilities in software, how potential attackers can use those vulnerabilities to their advantage, and recommending security mitigating measures to mitigate those vulnerabilities.</p>
<p>In their report, Penetrum found that “after extensive research, we have found that not only is TikTok a massive security flaw waiting to happen, but the ties that they have to Chinese parties and Chinese ISP’s make it a very vulnerable source of data.”</p>
<p><a href="https://penetrum.com/tiktok/Penetrum_TikTok_Security_Analysis_whitepaper.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer ">According to the report</a>, TikTok collects the following user data:
“</p>
<ul>
<li>IMEI number of a phone,</li>
<li>Screen Resolution,</li>
<li>SIM card provider</li>
<li>Tracks the smartphone’s location</li>
<li>Collects GPS coordinates</li>
<li>Collects WiFi location and SSID-changes</li>
<li>Collects Mobile Cell Data</li>
<li>O.S. version</li>
<li>Full lists of mobile contacts</li>
<li>SMS logs</li>
<li>IMSI numbers</li>
<li>Smartphone model</li>
<li>Smartphone version</li>
<li>Stored app data from previous installations, and</li>
<li>Memory data”</li>
</ul>
<p>According to the report, this amount of data “creates an extremely realistic and graphic fingerprint of your phone which can be used to determine everything you have installed.” Furthermore, “the IMSI which is used to follow users while getting a new phone, basically while transferring your SIM data to a new phone, the IMSI number stays with you.” This enables the application owner to “create a profile on you.” The report states that “TikTok does an excessive amount of tracking on it’s users, and that the data collected is partially if not fully stored on Chinese servers”</p>
<p>In addition to the information collected by the application, the report presents several “Security Concerns of Downloading TikTok.” In more detail, the following:</p>
<p>“</p>
<ul>
<li>Execution of O.S. commands</li>
<li>Insecure cryptography usage</li>
<li>Potential SQL injection code from user defined variables</li>
<li>Storing of API tokens</li>
<li>Webview enabled by default along with insecure webview enabled”</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="what-does-all-of-the-above-mean">What does all of the above mean?</h3>
<p>It means that TikTok has vulnerabilities that, if known by someone “who figures out how to enable and leverage this capability of this app, can use it or execute man in the middle attacks.” Why? Because the vulnerabilities mentioned in the report can potentially load files on the smartphone, “which in theory can lead to malware being loaded from inside the application, chained with remote debugging to see what fails in your malware. It also allows a very big window for attackers to not only upload, but execute, and debug their malware as well(in almost real time).” To Penetrum “this seems like an extreme security risk that shouldn’t be taken lightly.”</p>
<p>If the conclusions of the Security Analysis report are accurate, then the concerns that Governments have had about security risks to government information are warranted. However, if the findings are accurate, government staff are profiled and constantly tracked. This could mean a potential adversary could plan, prepare, and execute intelligence operations to recruit government staff as spies.</p>
<p>Based on <a href="https://penetrum.com/tiktok/Penetrum_TikTok_Security_Analysis_whitepaper.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer ">Penetrum’s Security Analysis report</a>, if accurate, TikTok could be considered an intelligence collection tool to collect government information and profile, government staff. A threat actor could use this intelligence to always stay one step ahead of, for example, the U.K. government in political, military, economic, social, infrastructure, and information affairs. This could pose a national security risk.</p>
<p>One case that reminds of this approach is what <a href="https://americanmilitarynews.com/2020/12/china-exposed-cia-operatives-in-africa-and-europe-with-hacked-us-data-report-says/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer ">American Military News states</a>: “In 2012, China hacked a major U.S. Office of Personnel Management (OPM) database which allowed them to expose numerous CIA spies operating in Africa and Europe.</p>
<p><a href="https://foreignpolicy.com/2020/12/21/china-stolen-us-data-exposed-cia-operatives-spy-networks/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer ">Foreign Policy states</a>, “During the OPM breach, Chinese hackers stole detailed, often highly sensitive personnel data from 21.5 million current and former U.S. officials, their spouses, and job applicants, including health, residency, employment, fingerprint, and financial data.”</p>
<p>The difference between the OPM hack and TikTok is that current and future government staff freely provide this kind of information, especially since TikTok collects all of the information, as noted above. At the same time, those aware of TikTok’s capabilities can conduct eavesdropping attacks and not need to “hack” into government databases (although if vulnerabilities exist, that is also likely to happen).</p>
<p>Therefore, the U.K. Cabinet Office announcing a “<a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/tiktok-banned-on-uk-government-devices-as-part-of-wider-app-review" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer ">precautionary ban on TikTok on government</a>” electronic devices does not protect only sensitive information but also government staff: current and future.</p>
]]></description>
</item>
<item>
    <title>The Cyber Threat Landscape and its Implications for Civil Organizations</title>
    <link>https://cyberoperationer.github.io/2023/the-cyber-threat-landscape-and-its-implications-for-civil-organizations/</link>
    <pubDate>Wed, 15 Mar 2023 14:41:58 &#43;0100</pubDate>
    <author>CO</author>
    <guid>https://cyberoperationer.github.io/2023/the-cyber-threat-landscape-and-its-implications-for-civil-organizations/</guid>
    <description><![CDATA[<h3 id="today-i-had-the-honor-of-presenting-on-the-cyber-threat-landscape-and-its-implications-for-civil-organizations-the-increased-interconnectedness-provides-many-opportunities-but-at-the-same-time-threat-actors-and-their-behavior-can-put-individuals-and-organizations-at-risk">Today I had the honor of presenting on the cyber threat landscape and its implications for civil organizations. The increased interconnectedness provides many opportunities, but at the same time, threat actors and their behavior can put individuals and organizations at risk.</h3>
<p>The purpose was to:</p>
<ul>
<li>Minimize risks to staff, assets, and operations.</li>
<li>Raise awareness of possible threats and related tactics, techniques, and procedures, and</li>
<li>Present some cases to illustrate the impact of successful cyber attacks against companies.</li>
</ul>
<p>The objective of the training was to raise staff awareness. After the presentation, staff can:</p>
<ul>
<li>Understand the cyber threat landscape and its potential impact on civilian organizations;</li>
<li>Describe the tactics, techniques, and procedures used by threat actors to enter an organization; and</li>
<li>Take practical measures to prevent, avoid, or mitigate intrusion risks.</li>
</ul>
<p>Cyber Security topics that were covered included:</p>
<ul>
<li>Cyber security at home,</li>
<li>In the office, and</li>
<li>During travel.</li>
</ul>
<p>Thank you to the organization for inviting me to speak about an important topic!</p>
]]></description>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Digital Geopolitics: A Review of the Current State</title>
    <link>https://cyberoperationer.github.io/2023/digital-geopolitics-a-review-of-the-current-state/</link>
    <pubDate>Tue, 14 Mar 2023 17:20:31 &#43;0100</pubDate>
    <author>CO</author>
    <guid>https://cyberoperationer.github.io/2023/digital-geopolitics-a-review-of-the-current-state/</guid>
    <description><![CDATA[<p></p>
<h3 id="my-latest-articlehttpspapersacademic-conferencesorgindexphpiccwsarticleview955947-at-the-19th-international-conference-on-cyber-warfare-and-security-towson-university-raises-the-question-what-is-the-current-state-of-digital-geopolitics"><a href="https://papers.academic-conferences.org/index.php/iccws/article/view/955/947" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer ">My latest article</a> at the 19th International Conference on Cyber Warfare and Security, Towson University, raises the question what is the current state of digital geopolitics?</h3>
<p>There is no technology that has transformed societies in the ways that information- and telecommunications technology (ITC) has. The increased pace of digitalization has opened opportunities to conduct e-commerce, e-governance, streamline processes, but also transformed intelligence, surveillance, reconnaissance, and command and control of joint military operations.</p>
<p>There needs to be more research on the topic. It is essential to review the scientific literature and see what has previously done.</p>
<p>The review shows cyberspace affects all domains of human life and the political, military, economic, social, information and infrastructure systems and subsystems. Technology and Information are the two key areas that are affecting digital geopolitics.</p>
<p>The article aims to raise awareness among policymakers, authorities, and the public about how technologies are used for disinformation, foreign interference, and freedom of expression.</p>
]]></description>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Offensive Cyberspace Operations for Cyber Security</title>
    <link>https://cyberoperationer.github.io/2023/offensive-cyberspace-operations-for-cyber-security/</link>
    <pubDate>Fri, 10 Mar 2023 11:40:12 &#43;0200</pubDate>
    <author>CO</author>
    <guid>https://cyberoperationer.github.io/2023/offensive-cyberspace-operations-for-cyber-security/</guid>
    <description><![CDATA[<h3 id="my-latest-articlehttpspapersacademic-conferencesorgindexphpiccwsarticleview1054952-at-the-19th-international-conference-on-cyber-warfare-and-security-towson-university-raises-the-question-of-what-are-offensive-cyberspace-operations-for-cyber-security-and-why-now"><a href="https://papers.academic-conferences.org/index.php/iccws/article/view/1054/952" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer ">My latest article</a> at the 19th International Conference on Cyber Warfare and Security, Towson University, raises the question of what are offensive cyberspace operations for cyber security, and why now?</h3>
<p>Offensive cyberspace operations are actions taken by an organized group of people with a defined purpose. The purpose is to take down an adversary’s devices, infrastructure, and tools. By taking the fight to the adversary, it may be possible to make them switch stance: from conducting attacks to defending themselves. These actions ensure cyber security.</p>
<p>There needs to be more research on the topic. It is essential to review the scientific literature and see what previous researchers have done and their thoughts at that time. Much information exists today thanks to mainstream media reporting on the topic. And this reporting is thanks to government agencies successfully halting adversary attacks.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/national-security/2022/12/22/cybercom-russia-iran-attacks/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer ">U.S. Cyber Command has protected the U.S. 2018-midterm elections by dismantling the infrastructure of a Russian troll farm</a>. This example shows how the command for cyberspace can use offensive cyberspace operations to ensure the cyber security of elections.</p>
<p>The article aims to raise awareness among policymakers, authorities, and the public about the success of offensive cyberspace operations for cyber security.</p>
]]></description>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
