<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>All Posts - Cyberspace Operations</title>
        <link>https://cyberoperationer.github.io/posts/</link>
        <description>All Posts | Cyberspace Operations</description>
        <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><managingEditor>g.huskaj@gcsp.ch (CO)</managingEditor>
            <webMaster>g.huskaj@gcsp.ch (CO)</webMaster><lastBuildDate>Thu, 14 Sep 2023 22:44:21 &#43;0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cyberoperationer.github.io/posts/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" /><item>
    <title>Digital Geopolitics and the Imperative of Cyber Diplomacy: Shaping a Unified and Secure Cyberspace</title>
    <link>https://cyberoperationer.github.io/2023/digital-geopolitics-and-the-imperative-of-cyber-diplomacy-shaping-a-unified-and-secure-cyberspace/</link>
    <pubDate>Thu, 14 Sep 2023 22:44:21 &#43;0200</pubDate>
    <author>CO</author>
    <guid>https://cyberoperationer.github.io/2023/digital-geopolitics-and-the-imperative-of-cyber-diplomacy-shaping-a-unified-and-secure-cyberspace/</guid>
    <description><![CDATA[<p></p>
<p><strong>Note to readers:</strong> I was scheduled to participate in the panel discussion at the CyberPeace Summit 2023. However, due to unforeseen timing constraints and prior obligations that I could not reschedule, I was regrettably unable to present my intervention. As I believe the contents of this speech are critical and worth sharing, I have decided to publish it here for the broader audience. While I wasn’t able to deliver these thoughts virtually, I hope they provide value and insight to those interested in the topic.</p>
<hr>
<p>Ladies and Gentlemen,
Esteemed delegates,</p>
<p>Good morning. Good day and afternoon. I want to thank the Global CyberPeace Summit and Dialogues for organising and hosting this important event. As the title of this panel states, Internet Governance and Cyber Policy Dialogue have a role to play in ensuring an open and resilient cyberspace that benefits all humankind.</p>
<p>Today, I will highlight incidents and their consequences, discuss cyber diplomacy, and touch upon digital geopolitics. The critical interplay between diplomacy and cyberspace will become more evident by the end.</p>
<p>This is more critical than you may think:</p>
<p>Imagine if threat actors could infiltrate companies managing the IT of thousands of clients.</p>
<p>In 2017, a report was released detailing cyber espionage campaigns of another country. The report uses various analysis methods to attribute the cyber espionage campaign to a specific threat actor.</p>
<p>The attackers targeted companies that manage their customer&rsquo;s IT and systems. These companies, also known as managed systems providers, have access to their customer&rsquo;s networks.</p>
<p>As you can imagine, managed systems providers are very lucrative targets for cyber espionage attacks.</p>
<p>According to the report, once a threat actor has gained access, and I quote, &ldquo;it is likely to be relatively straightforward to exploit this and move laterally onto the networks of potentially thousands of other victims.&rdquo;</p>
<p>The targets included industries, and I quote, in &ldquo;information technology, high-tech electronics, financial services, satellites and telecommunications, energy, public administration, scientific research and consulting, chemicals, and aerospace.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Another threat actor has targeted governments, private companies, the media, and other organisations.</p>
<p>What are the implications of cyber espionage campaigns?
In 2014, three world-leading companies suffered cyber espionage. In 2017, one filed for bankruptcy, one declared bankruptcy, and the third traded at less than half of pre-attack levels.</p>
<p>Let&rsquo;s discuss some other attacks.
In 2021, threat actors conducted a ransomware attack on Colonial Pipeline. Colonial Pipeline is the largest refined products pipeline in the United States, transporting more than 100 million gallons or 2.5 million barrels per day. Colonial transports approximately 45 per cent of all fuel consumed on the East Coast, providing refined products to more than 50 million Americans.</p>
<p>The threat actors demanded 75 bitcoins, which were equivalent to USD 4.4 million at that time. This attack impacted the US&rsquo;s political, economic, and social systems.</p>
<p>In 2021, a private company stated that a threat actor was inside another neighbouring country&rsquo;s energy and power plant&rsquo;s IT systems.</p>
<p>In 2022, just as the Russian aggression towards Ukraine began, Ukrainian agencies were hit by cyberattacks. In addition, the cyberattacks also hit satellite operator Viasat. Why? The threat actor intended to attack Ukrainian military command and control systems. However, the attack had secondary/tertiary effects by striking civilian infrastructure operated by Viasat.</p>
<p>These examples showcase how national security interests are furthered in and through cyberspace.</p>
<p>Cyberspace is increasingly used for cyberespionage, cyber-ransom attacks, misinformation, and disinformation campaigns, attacking the information environment and, in turn, the cognitive dimension of humans.</p>
<p>These incidents offer a backdrop for the importance of our discussion today.</p>
<p>Therefore, we must understand the challenges to tackle them together.</p>
<p>So what do we do about this?
Cyber diplomacy and dialogue have a vital role to play, and so does deterrence.</p>
<p>I published a research article reviewing the policy landscape of cyber deterrence and dialogue. In 2017, scholars said, and I quote, &ldquo;protecting or advancing national interests cannot merely rely on deterrence: shaping behaviour requires &lsquo;active cyber operations&rsquo;.&rdquo;</p>
<p>In 2018, another scholar stated that Information systems are always vulnerable: states that are &ldquo;not constrained by the etiquette and rules of Western law&rdquo; will exercise cyber power by combining it with &ldquo;conventional military and intelligence assets.&rdquo;</p>
<p>In 2019, a third scholar covered the topic of a policy of persistent engagement, strategic stability, superiority, and forward defence. The same year, a framework to assess policy in persistent engagement was published.</p>
<p>Additionally, in 2019, another scholar reviewed the opportunities and limits that international law provides.</p>
<p>In 2020, a different scholar stated, &ldquo;There is opportunity to shape behaviour in cyberspace, but so are potential risks of escalation.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;The prospects of this strategy are ambiguous&rdquo;, and only through the &ldquo;accumulation of empirical experience in the application of this strategy&rdquo; will the advantages become apparent.</p>
<p>The same scholar said that diplomatic dialogue, be it behind the scenes or covert dialogue, is critical to ensure that communication between states occurs at all levels, from peace to crisis and un-peace.</p>
<p>And Cyber Diplomacy does indeed have a role to play.</p>
<p>Remember the Colonial Pipeline case I mentioned earlier? Once Colonial Pipeline identified the attack, they contacted a cyber security company to investigate and respond.</p>
<p>They also notified Law enforcement and the federal government authorities of the attack. The pipeline was taken offline to reduce the risk of exposure to the operational network. The CEO of Colonial Pipeline took the difficult decision to pay the ransom of 75 bitcoins ($4.4 million).</p>
<p>On the political level, President Joe Biden declared the event a state emergency. The Department of Justice gave US agencies and their allies the legal authority to recover the bitcoins, approximately USD 2.3 million.</p>
<p>Finally, in June 2021, at the President Biden and President Putin summit in Geneva, the two Presidents held a dialogue on arms control cybersecurity and the Colonial Pipeline ransomware attack.</p>
<p>This is just one illustration of how crucial cyber diplomacy and global collaboration are in today&rsquo;s interconnected globe.</p>
<p>Cyberspace has also implications for digital geopolitics. In another research article I published, it became evident that technology has always been at the heart of geopolitics.</p>
<p>When we were exploring the seas, it became vital to secure sea transport lanes. This led to the notion of Sea power.</p>
<p>As technology and innovation continued and the discovery of the steam engine, we had trains that could transport resources faster than sea transport. Thus, it became vital to secure these transports, hence land power.</p>
<p>And with the discovery of the aeroplane, we could transport traditional mail and other resources even faster. Hence, it was essential to discuss air power.</p>
<p>The same logic applies to space power. And today, with these cyber systems that are the backbone of everything we do online, it is crucial to discuss cyber power.</p>
<p>Therefore, digital geopolitics is about analysing internetworked information systems, or cyberspace, that, combined with geographic features of Earth and space, impact world politics and a country&rsquo;s political, military, economic and social systems.</p>
<p>It is evident that malign entities exploit vulnerabilities for cyber espionage and cyber attacks.</p>
<p>Furthermore, malign entities use cyberspace to conduct misinformation and disinformation campaigns. The target here is humankind&rsquo;s cognitive vulnerabilities.</p>
<p>The consequence of cyber attacks on companies is that some go bankrupt.</p>
<p>The consequences of misinformation and disinformation are that some citizen groups engage in hate speech and violence.</p>
<p>One policy response has been the notion of cyber deterrence and persistent engagement. But what encapsulates everything is that cyber diplomacy and dialogue always have a role to play.</p>
<p>Let us not be deterred by malign entities because we know that digital geopolitics impacts a state&rsquo;s political, military, economic and social systems.</p>
<p>Together, through cyber diplomacy and dialogue, we&rsquo;re not just combating cyber threats but ensuring that current and future generations enjoy an open and resilient cyberspace that benefits all humankind.</p>
<p>Thank you again to the Global CyberPeace Summit and Dialogues for organising and hosting this important event. I wish you fruitful dialogue and discussions on these very important topics.</p>
<p>Thank you.</p>
]]></description>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Guiding the Future of Cyber Security Policy: The Importance of Supervision</title>
    <link>https://cyberoperationer.github.io/2023/guiding-the-future-of-cyber-security-policy-the-importance-of-supervision/</link>
    <pubDate>Fri, 23 Jun 2023 11:43:48 &#43;0200</pubDate>
    <author>CO</author>
    <guid>https://cyberoperationer.github.io/2023/guiding-the-future-of-cyber-security-policy-the-importance-of-supervision/</guid>
    <description><![CDATA[<p></p>
<h3 id="cyber-security-definitions-and-agencies">Cyber Security, Definitions and Agencies</h3>
<p>Cyber Security is a fundamental pillar and of utmost importance to secure our reliance on interconnected information systems in networks of networks facilitated by information and telecommunication technologies. Supervising two extraordinary individuals participating in the <a href="https://www.gcsp.ch/courses/leadership-international-security-course-lisc-2023-2024" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer ">Leadership in International Security Course (LISC)</a>, a highly competitive eight-month course in international security designed for high-performing professionals seeking to enhance their careers and effectively respond to the world&rsquo;s most pressing security challenges, has been a transformative journey: a journey where it not only underlines the importance of not only cyber security but also the invaluable role of guidance and supervision in updating and deepening the knowledge of the participants in the cyber security policy field.</p>
<p>Cyber Security has many definitions; some include process, people and technology, others focus on the technology level, such as protecting computers, electronic communication systems, services etc., and others focus on the policy level. Regardless of level, organisations must ensure their systems are cyber secure against cyber threat actors and related attacks. Organisations with insecure systems risk, for example, ransomware attacks. The implications can be devastating, from losing trust, their brand taking damage, or even threatening national security.</p>
<p>Intelligence communities, agencies responsible for cyber security, and private sector companies in the cyber security industry constantly present reports on the threat landscape. Firstly, the threat level is high in cyberspace because connected assets are always online and accessible, which means attackers can always target them. Second, threat actors, especially those in the Ransomeware-as-a-Service (RaaS)-sector, constantly seek ways to penetrate systems. Therefore, cyber security is a continuously shifting field requiring a highly skilled workforce. Therefore, cyber security is a continually shifting field requiring a highly skilled workforce. The importance of supervision becomes evident in this context.</p>
<h3 id="the-role-of-supervision">The Role of Supervision</h3>
<p>Over the eight-month LISC course, two brilliant LISC participants chose their respective cybersecurity-related topics, and I had the privilege of supervising them. The role of supervision is not only to impart knowledge; it is also about acting as a guide and mentor, and <a href="https://www.ucl.ac.uk/teaching-learning/publications/2019/aug/research-and-project-supervision-all-levels-introduction" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer ">source of information</a></p>
<h3 id="the-importance-of-individual-cyber-security-policy-research">The Importance of Individual Cyber Security Policy Research</h3>
<p>Under my supervision, the two LISC participants began their individual journeys. The first focused on &ldquo;Digital and Technological Sovereignty of the European Union&rdquo;, with a background on how technology and related components increasingly impact national security, providing challenges and opportunities for the EU and policy recommendations. The second focused on &ldquo;Public-Private Partnerships in Cybersecurity&rdquo; for successful collective cybersecurity by applying complexity theory in public-private partnerships and interviewing key stakeholders to present relevant policy recommendations.</p>
<p>Their research underscores the many facets and perspectives in cyber security. Each challenge requires unique approaches, and each participant&rsquo;s existing training, education, and expertise, augmented by the LISC program, can provide novel and relevant policy recommendations. The beauty of supervision lies in its ability to allow me to guide and support LISC participants as they delve into their unique paths, providing a significant, original contribution to cyber security policy knowledge.</p>
<h3 id="conclusions">Conclusions</h3>
<p>Technological advancements are occurring at exponential rates, so we cannot overstate the importance of cyber security and the role of dedicated &ldquo;pracademic&rdquo; (= professional and academic) supervision. Through guidance, mentorship and active engagement, we can identify and support the next generation of cyber security policy experts that ensure the safety and security of cyberspace. It has been an honour to guide these two future leaders in cyber security policy.
I look forward to their contributions to their organisations and countries for national and international security.</p>
]]></description>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Digital Authoritarianism: A Summary</title>
    <link>https://cyberoperationer.github.io/2023/digital-authoritarianism-a-summary/</link>
    <pubDate>Tue, 25 Apr 2023 21:12:28 &#43;0200</pubDate>
    <author>CO</author>
    <guid>https://cyberoperationer.github.io/2023/digital-authoritarianism-a-summary/</guid>
    <description><![CDATA[<p></p>
<h3 id="on-24-april-2023-the-us-director-of-national-intelligence-dni-dr-avril-haines-was-invited-to-a-public-conversation-with-carnegies-dan-baer-on-combatting-digital-authoritarianism-this-is-a-summary-of-her-presentation-the-entire-presentation-including-the-qa-session-is-on-carnegie-endowments-youtube-pagehttpswwwyoutubecomwatchvmd64c-dunyo">On 24 April 2023, The US Director of National Intelligence (DNI) Dr. Avril Haines was invited to a public conversation with Carnegie’s Dan Baer on combatting digital authoritarianism. This is a summary of her presentation. The entire presentation including the Q&amp;A session is on <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=mD64C-DUNYo" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer ">Carnegie Endowment&rsquo;s YouTube-page</a>.</h3>
<p>Today, democracy is increasingly challenged by autocratic leaders that contest over information, defined as “the increasing use of digital technology to promote authoritarianism.” The DNI highlighted the importance of intellectual exchange between the intelligence community and think tanks like Carnegie Endowment to “challenge our thinking and work to ensure that we are focused on what matters, and not missing the broader strategic pictures.” This collaboration is especially fruitful in understanding the landscape, addressing the problem, and focus in one aspect of a problem.</p>
<p>The aspect the DNI was commenting was “the degree to which new technologies, institutional, legal, and organisational approaches to digital repression being deployed by authoritarian governments and exported to other countries are advancing authoritarianism and undermining democratic governance globally.”</p>
<p>The DNI covered seven themes in her presentation. First, the distinction between an intelligence service in a democracy versus an authoritarian state. Second, why digital repression is a critical threat to national security. Third, how foreign governments are “increasingly using digital information and communication technologies to monitor and suppress political debate domestically as well as in their expat and diaspora communities abroad.” Fourth, describing the Russian, Chinese and Iranian models and methods “that are being exported.” Fifth, how governments are increasingly using spyware to “target political opponents and critics.” Sixth, how governments are using technologies to limit user access to information. Finally, the DNI describes how the intelligence community “alongside the private sector and research institutions can help to create greater awareness regarding the types of technologies as well as the institutional legal and organisational approaches being used to engage in digital repression.”</p>
<h3 id="intelligence-services-in-democracies-vs-an-authoritarian-state">Intelligence services in democracies vs. an authoritarian State</h3>
<p>According to the DNI, Intelligence services in democracies:
“are subject to democratically passed laws, have internal and external safeguards in place and ultimately are held accountable to oversight mechanisms that work to ensure we remain legal, ethical, and focused on providing the best intelligence to help decision makers in our government make better national security and foreign policy decisions while being protective of people&rsquo;s civil liberties and privacy.”</p>
<p>In authoritarian countries, intelligence services are “often used as tools of the state to enhance digital repression under the direction of their rulers.”</p>
<p>Why is Digital Repression a Critical Threat to National Security?
Authoritarian States are increasingly using digital technology to promote authoritarianism. Free flows of information pose a threat and authoritarian countries were early concerned with the Internet and the implications of free flows of information. The Arab Spring uprising “served as a turning point when authoritarian governments came to recognise that their public’s digital connectivity posed an existential threat to their grip on power.” Therefore, using digital technologies to control the flows of information, eliminate dissent, remould society, conduct mass surveillance, spread disinformation, misinformation, and propaganda, and use spyware to suppress voices and debate, authoritarian States are exporting authoritarianism which is a risk to the integrity of democracy and democratic societies.</p>
<h3 id="china">China</h3>
<p>The People&rsquo;s Republic of China (PRC) is a “global leader in digital repression”, topping Freedom House&rsquo;s list of countries with the least internet freedom for eight consecutive years. China excels at censoring digital information and surveilling its population due to early prioritization of digital controls. The PRC uses digital repression to prevent challenges to its rule, eliminate dissent, and reshape society for national rejuvenation.</p>
<p>China presents its use of digital repression tools as features, controlling information flow and limiting citizen access to information that may undermine the government&rsquo;s legitimacy. The country exports its technology and know-how, enabling transnational repression and assisting other governments in digital repression within their borders.</p>
<p>Chinese smart cities integrate surveillance technology with public goods provision, such as traffic safety, to exert authoritarian control. The PRC is also the leading perpetrator of transnational repression, often through digital means, with its Operation Fox Hunt initiative. Recently, the EU&rsquo;s Department of Justice charged PRC police officers for using fake social media accounts to spread propaganda and harass dissidents in the United States.</p>
<h3 id="russia">Russia</h3>
<p>Russia is also a leading perpetrator of digital repression, taking a different approach from China by relying on complex legal and institutional structures to control information. It has been particularly active in spreading disinformation since the start of Putin&rsquo;s illegal invasion of Ukraine. Internet freedom in Russia is the 6th least free globally and reached an all-time low last year.</p>
<p>The Kremlin has blocked social media sites and thousands of websites and introduced harsh penalties for spreading “false” information about the Russia-Ukraine conflict. Moscow has pressured foreign IT giants to abide by its content moderation requirements, resulting in increased self-censorship and withdrawal from the Russian media space. The expansion of Kremlin-aligned media corporations, such as VKontakte&rsquo;s acquisition of Yandex, has given the government greater control over online content.</p>
<p>In 2022, Moscow required foreign IT and media companies with significant Russian user bases to maintain local offices and comply with Russian laws. The government has encouraged the development of indigenous platforms to replace foreign social media companies, allowing for increased content control. Russia has also undermined internet freedom in Ukraine through internet shutdowns, cyberattacks, targeted airstrikes, and dismantling of telecommunications infrastructure.</p>
<p>A Russia-based influence operation in Ukraine was discovered last September, involving over 60 websites impersonating news organizations and accounts on major U.S. social media platforms.</p>
<h3 id="iran">Iran</h3>
<p>Iran imposes Internet shutdowns to stop protests, such as during the protests after the death of 22-year-old Mahsa Amini in police custody. During the protests, Iran conducted 18 Internet shutdowns. Furthermore, Iran has presented its intent and capability to use proxies such as an Eastern European criminal organisation to suppress dissidents by murdering them: a human rights activist was murdered after criticizing Iran’s treatment of women.</p>
<h3 id="other-tactics-techniques-and-procedures-ttps">Other Tactics Techniques and Procedures (TTPs)</h3>
<p>Other countries are adopting the approaches mentioned for digital repression. Additional tactics include the tactic of internet shutdowns, blocking websites, using commercial spyware, to provide only access “to an online space that mirrors the views of their government and its interests”, limiting “users access to information sources located outside of their borders”, monitoring populations and “potentially manipulate control and exploit information based on the insights gained from the” vast amounts of data created by billions and trillions of internet of things-devices connected to smart city initiatives, and exploiting facial recognition AI to quell political unrest.</p>
<h3 id="the-response-to-digital-repression">The Response to Digital Repression</h3>
<p>Collaboration between the intelligence community, private sector, and research institutions is crucial. Raising awareness about technologies and approaches used for digital repression, we can help develop normative frameworks that preserve the positive potential for these technologies while guarding against their repressive uses. This should include promoting technical standards and design approaches that support cybersecurity, democratic governance, freedom of expression, and political discourse, while acknowledging the risks associated with vast data collection. In addition, modern laws and organizational structures are needed to make digital repression more difficult. As certain governments become more adept at using repressive technologies, urgent action is required to address the growing sophistication of automated surveillance and identity resolution techniques.</p>
<p>Digital repression and foreign malign influence are whole-of-society challenges that require a unified response to protect the integrity of democratic societies worldwide.</p>
<h3 id="a-detailed-model-of-digital-repression">A Detailed Model of Digital Repression</h3>
<p>This section presents a detailed model of digital repression based on the presentation.
</p>
<p>Due to China being an earlier adopter of Digital Controls, it is more mature in controlling information flows. Russia, on the other hand, is working to get there. Finally, Iran will likely need a higher level of maturity in digital controls and therefore currently relies on simply shutting down their portion of the internet combined with deterrence by punishment and fear manifesting in for example, <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/world/ng-interactive/2022/oct/31/mapping-irans-unrest-how-mahsa-aminis-death-led-to-nationwide-protests" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer ">crackdowns</a>.</p>
]]></description>
</item>
<item>
    <title>TikTok banned on Government Electronic Devices</title>
    <link>https://cyberoperationer.github.io/2023/tiktok-banned-on-government-electronic-devices/</link>
    <pubDate>Mon, 20 Mar 2023 00:51:25 &#43;0100</pubDate>
    <author>CO</author>
    <guid>https://cyberoperationer.github.io/2023/tiktok-banned-on-government-electronic-devices/</guid>
    <description><![CDATA[<h1 id="on-16-march-2023-the-uk-cabinet-office-announced-that-the-social-media-app-tiktok-is-banned-on-government-electronic-deviceshttpswwwgovukgovernmentnewstiktok-banned-on-uk-government-devices-as-part-of-wider-app-review-the-reason"><a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/tiktok-banned-on-uk-government-devices-as-part-of-wider-app-review" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer ">On 16 March 2023, the U.K. Cabinet Office announced that the social media app TikTok is banned on government electronic devices</a>. The reason?</h1>
<h3 id="a-security-review-ordered-by-the-cabinet-office-ministers-aimed-to-look-at-the-potential-vulnerability-of-government-data-from-social-media-apps-on-devices-and-risks-around-how-sensitive-information-could-be-accessed-and-used-by-some-platforms">A security review ordered by the Cabinet Office Ministers aimed to look “at the potential vulnerability of government data from social media apps on devices and risks around how sensitive information could be accessed and used by some platforms.”</h3>
<p><a href="https://www.euronews.com/next/2023/03/17/which-countries-have-banned-tiktok-cybersecurity-data-privacy-espionage-fears" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer ">Euronews</a> reported on 17 March 2023 that in addition to the U.K., “New Zealand, The European Parliament, European Commission, and the E.U. Council,…, Belgium, Canada, Denmark, India, Taiwan, and the United States” have banned TikTok from government devices. Euronews reports that Afghanistan and Pakistan have also banned the app.</p>
<p>Their concerns are warranted.</p>
<p>On 4 July 2022, <a href="https://internet2-0.com/technical-analysis-of-tiktok-app/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer ">internet2.0</a> presented the “Technical Analysis of TikTok App.” Their media release provided a link to <a href="https://penetrum.com/tiktok/Penetrum_TikTok_Security_Analysis_whitepaper.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer ">Penetrum</a>, who conducted a Security Analysis on TikTok. Security Analysis is a process of identifying vulnerabilities in software, how potential attackers can use those vulnerabilities to their advantage, and recommending security mitigating measures to mitigate those vulnerabilities.</p>
<p>In their report, Penetrum found that “after extensive research, we have found that not only is TikTok a massive security flaw waiting to happen, but the ties that they have to Chinese parties and Chinese ISP’s make it a very vulnerable source of data.”</p>
<p><a href="https://penetrum.com/tiktok/Penetrum_TikTok_Security_Analysis_whitepaper.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer ">According to the report</a>, TikTok collects the following user data:
“</p>
<ul>
<li>IMEI number of a phone,</li>
<li>Screen Resolution,</li>
<li>SIM card provider</li>
<li>Tracks the smartphone’s location</li>
<li>Collects GPS coordinates</li>
<li>Collects WiFi location and SSID-changes</li>
<li>Collects Mobile Cell Data</li>
<li>O.S. version</li>
<li>Full lists of mobile contacts</li>
<li>SMS logs</li>
<li>IMSI numbers</li>
<li>Smartphone model</li>
<li>Smartphone version</li>
<li>Stored app data from previous installations, and</li>
<li>Memory data”</li>
</ul>
<p>According to the report, this amount of data “creates an extremely realistic and graphic fingerprint of your phone which can be used to determine everything you have installed.” Furthermore, “the IMSI which is used to follow users while getting a new phone, basically while transferring your SIM data to a new phone, the IMSI number stays with you.” This enables the application owner to “create a profile on you.” The report states that “TikTok does an excessive amount of tracking on it’s users, and that the data collected is partially if not fully stored on Chinese servers”</p>
<p>In addition to the information collected by the application, the report presents several “Security Concerns of Downloading TikTok.” In more detail, the following:</p>
<p>“</p>
<ul>
<li>Execution of O.S. commands</li>
<li>Insecure cryptography usage</li>
<li>Potential SQL injection code from user defined variables</li>
<li>Storing of API tokens</li>
<li>Webview enabled by default along with insecure webview enabled”</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="what-does-all-of-the-above-mean">What does all of the above mean?</h3>
<p>It means that TikTok has vulnerabilities that, if known by someone “who figures out how to enable and leverage this capability of this app, can use it or execute man in the middle attacks.” Why? Because the vulnerabilities mentioned in the report can potentially load files on the smartphone, “which in theory can lead to malware being loaded from inside the application, chained with remote debugging to see what fails in your malware. It also allows a very big window for attackers to not only upload, but execute, and debug their malware as well(in almost real time).” To Penetrum “this seems like an extreme security risk that shouldn’t be taken lightly.”</p>
<p>If the conclusions of the Security Analysis report are accurate, then the concerns that Governments have had about security risks to government information are warranted. However, if the findings are accurate, government staff are profiled and constantly tracked. This could mean a potential adversary could plan, prepare, and execute intelligence operations to recruit government staff as spies.</p>
<p>Based on <a href="https://penetrum.com/tiktok/Penetrum_TikTok_Security_Analysis_whitepaper.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer ">Penetrum’s Security Analysis report</a>, if accurate, TikTok could be considered an intelligence collection tool to collect government information and profile, government staff. A threat actor could use this intelligence to always stay one step ahead of, for example, the U.K. government in political, military, economic, social, infrastructure, and information affairs. This could pose a national security risk.</p>
<p>One case that reminds of this approach is what <a href="https://americanmilitarynews.com/2020/12/china-exposed-cia-operatives-in-africa-and-europe-with-hacked-us-data-report-says/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer ">American Military News states</a>: “In 2012, China hacked a major U.S. Office of Personnel Management (OPM) database which allowed them to expose numerous CIA spies operating in Africa and Europe.</p>
<p><a href="https://foreignpolicy.com/2020/12/21/china-stolen-us-data-exposed-cia-operatives-spy-networks/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer ">Foreign Policy states</a>, “During the OPM breach, Chinese hackers stole detailed, often highly sensitive personnel data from 21.5 million current and former U.S. officials, their spouses, and job applicants, including health, residency, employment, fingerprint, and financial data.”</p>
<p>The difference between the OPM hack and TikTok is that current and future government staff freely provide this kind of information, especially since TikTok collects all of the information, as noted above. At the same time, those aware of TikTok’s capabilities can conduct eavesdropping attacks and not need to “hack” into government databases (although if vulnerabilities exist, that is also likely to happen).</p>
<p>Therefore, the U.K. Cabinet Office announcing a “<a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/tiktok-banned-on-uk-government-devices-as-part-of-wider-app-review" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer ">precautionary ban on TikTok on government</a>” electronic devices does not protect only sensitive information but also government staff: current and future.</p>
]]></description>
</item>
<item>
    <title>The Cyber Threat Landscape and its Implications for Civil Organizations</title>
    <link>https://cyberoperationer.github.io/2023/the-cyber-threat-landscape-and-its-implications-for-civil-organizations/</link>
    <pubDate>Wed, 15 Mar 2023 14:41:58 &#43;0100</pubDate>
    <author>CO</author>
    <guid>https://cyberoperationer.github.io/2023/the-cyber-threat-landscape-and-its-implications-for-civil-organizations/</guid>
    <description><![CDATA[<h3 id="today-i-had-the-honor-of-presenting-on-the-cyber-threat-landscape-and-its-implications-for-civil-organizations-the-increased-interconnectedness-provides-many-opportunities-but-at-the-same-time-threat-actors-and-their-behavior-can-put-individuals-and-organizations-at-risk">Today I had the honor of presenting on the cyber threat landscape and its implications for civil organizations. The increased interconnectedness provides many opportunities, but at the same time, threat actors and their behavior can put individuals and organizations at risk.</h3>
<p>The purpose was to:</p>
<ul>
<li>Minimize risks to staff, assets, and operations.</li>
<li>Raise awareness of possible threats and related tactics, techniques, and procedures, and</li>
<li>Present some cases to illustrate the impact of successful cyber attacks against companies.</li>
</ul>
<p>The objective of the training was to raise staff awareness. After the presentation, staff can:</p>
<ul>
<li>Understand the cyber threat landscape and its potential impact on civilian organizations;</li>
<li>Describe the tactics, techniques, and procedures used by threat actors to enter an organization; and</li>
<li>Take practical measures to prevent, avoid, or mitigate intrusion risks.</li>
</ul>
<p>Cyber Security topics that were covered included:</p>
<ul>
<li>Cyber security at home,</li>
<li>In the office, and</li>
<li>During travel.</li>
</ul>
<p>Thank you to the organization for inviting me to speak about an important topic!</p>
]]></description>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Digital Geopolitics: A Review of the Current State</title>
    <link>https://cyberoperationer.github.io/2023/digital-geopolitics-a-review-of-the-current-state/</link>
    <pubDate>Tue, 14 Mar 2023 17:20:31 &#43;0100</pubDate>
    <author>CO</author>
    <guid>https://cyberoperationer.github.io/2023/digital-geopolitics-a-review-of-the-current-state/</guid>
    <description><![CDATA[<p></p>
<h3 id="my-latest-articlehttpspapersacademic-conferencesorgindexphpiccwsarticleview955947-at-the-19th-international-conference-on-cyber-warfare-and-security-towson-university-raises-the-question-what-is-the-current-state-of-digital-geopolitics"><a href="https://papers.academic-conferences.org/index.php/iccws/article/view/955/947" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer ">My latest article</a> at the 19th International Conference on Cyber Warfare and Security, Towson University, raises the question what is the current state of digital geopolitics?</h3>
<p>There is no technology that has transformed societies in the ways that information- and telecommunications technology (ITC) has. The increased pace of digitalization has opened opportunities to conduct e-commerce, e-governance, streamline processes, but also transformed intelligence, surveillance, reconnaissance, and command and control of joint military operations.</p>
<p>There needs to be more research on the topic. It is essential to review the scientific literature and see what has previously done.</p>
<p>The review shows cyberspace affects all domains of human life and the political, military, economic, social, information and infrastructure systems and subsystems. Technology and Information are the two key areas that are affecting digital geopolitics.</p>
<p>The article aims to raise awareness among policymakers, authorities, and the public about how technologies are used for disinformation, foreign interference, and freedom of expression.</p>
]]></description>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Offensive Cyberspace Operations for Cyber Security</title>
    <link>https://cyberoperationer.github.io/2023/offensive-cyberspace-operations-for-cyber-security/</link>
    <pubDate>Fri, 10 Mar 2023 11:40:12 &#43;0200</pubDate>
    <author>CO</author>
    <guid>https://cyberoperationer.github.io/2023/offensive-cyberspace-operations-for-cyber-security/</guid>
    <description><![CDATA[<h3 id="my-latest-articlehttpspapersacademic-conferencesorgindexphpiccwsarticleview1054952-at-the-19th-international-conference-on-cyber-warfare-and-security-towson-university-raises-the-question-of-what-are-offensive-cyberspace-operations-for-cyber-security-and-why-now"><a href="https://papers.academic-conferences.org/index.php/iccws/article/view/1054/952" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer ">My latest article</a> at the 19th International Conference on Cyber Warfare and Security, Towson University, raises the question of what are offensive cyberspace operations for cyber security, and why now?</h3>
<p>Offensive cyberspace operations are actions taken by an organized group of people with a defined purpose. The purpose is to take down an adversary’s devices, infrastructure, and tools. By taking the fight to the adversary, it may be possible to make them switch stance: from conducting attacks to defending themselves. These actions ensure cyber security.</p>
<p>There needs to be more research on the topic. It is essential to review the scientific literature and see what previous researchers have done and their thoughts at that time. Much information exists today thanks to mainstream media reporting on the topic. And this reporting is thanks to government agencies successfully halting adversary attacks.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/national-security/2022/12/22/cybercom-russia-iran-attacks/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer ">U.S. Cyber Command has protected the U.S. 2018-midterm elections by dismantling the infrastructure of a Russian troll farm</a>. This example shows how the command for cyberspace can use offensive cyberspace operations to ensure the cyber security of elections.</p>
<p>The article aims to raise awareness among policymakers, authorities, and the public about the success of offensive cyberspace operations for cyber security.</p>
]]></description>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
