<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>All Posts - Cyberspace Operations</title>
        <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/</link>
        <description>All Posts | Cyberspace Operations</description>
        <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 08:54:12 &#43;0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/posts/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" /><item>
    <title>Executive Cyber Briefing – Last Week’s Risks in Context</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/2025/executive-cyber-briefing-last-weeks-risks-in-context/</link>
    <pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 08:54:12 &#43;0100</pubDate>
    <author>Author</author>
    <guid>http://localhost:1313/2025/executive-cyber-briefing-last-weeks-risks-in-context/</guid>
    <description><![CDATA[<p></p>
<p>Last week’s developments cluster around <strong>three themes</strong>:<br>
<strong>industrialised social-engineering pipelines</strong>, <strong>the uneven impact of AI-enabled tools on cybercrime</strong>, and <strong>the deepening entanglement of state cyber operations with physical security</strong>.</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="1-industrialised-social-engineering">1. Industrialised Social Engineering</h2>
<h3 id="dprk-job-fraud-malware--russian-activity-in-europe">DPRK Job-Fraud Malware &amp; Russian Activity in Europe</h3>
<p><strong>North Korea intensified its Contagious Interview and ClickFake Interview operations</strong>, adding <em>197 new malicious npm packages</em> downloaded more than <em>31,000 times</em>. These packages delivered updated <strong>OtterCookie</strong> variants combining credential theft, crypto-wallet harvesting, browser data collection, and remote-shell access.<br>
Source: <a href="https://thehackernews.com/2025/11/north-korean-hackers-deploy-197-npm.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer ">The Hacker News</a></p>
<p>The campaigns now reach beyond the familiar “DPRK IT-worker” schema: they weaponise <strong>recruitment and assessment workflows</strong>, using staged coding tasks, fake HR portals, and macOS decoy prompts to extract passwords and system information.</p>
<p><strong>In Europe</strong>, Polish authorities detained a Russian national accused of hacking local firms, manipulating databases, and entering the country illegally before obtaining refugee status.<br>
Source: <a href="https://therecord.media/poland-detains-russian-citizen-accused-of-hacks" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer ">The Record</a></p>
<p>The arrest fits a wider pattern: Warsaw has linked over <strong>30 individuals of multiple nationalities</strong> to sabotage, arson, and intelligence operations tied to Russia.</p>
<p><strong>Connecting the dots:</strong> these cases illustrate the same operational logic—<strong>targeting individuals performing routine tasks</strong> (job applicants, admins, employees) rather than exploiting technical vulnerabilities or zero-days. Human workflows remain high-yield access vectors.</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="2-ai-in-cybercrime">2. AI in Cybercrime</h2>
<h3 id="useful-for-novices-technically-limited-for-operators">Useful for Novices, Technically Limited for Operators</h3>
<p>Palo Alto Networks’ Unit 42 assessed <strong>WormGPT 4</strong> and <strong>KawaiiGPT</strong>, the two most prominent “dark LLMs” marketed as <em>“AI without boundaries.”</em><br>
Source: <a href="https://www.darkreading.com/threat-intelligence/dark-llms-petty-criminals" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer ">Dark Reading</a></p>
<p>Key findings:</p>
<ul>
<li>They generate <strong>basic phishing emails</strong>, <strong>simple exfiltration scripts</strong>, and boilerplate malware.</li>
<li>They hallucinate code and require human correction.</li>
<li>Their output is largely <strong>derivative of known malware</strong>, offering no breakthrough techniques.</li>
<li>No evidence suggests that dark LLMs are reshaping high-end intrusion workflows.</li>
</ul>
<p>These tools mainly support <strong>low-skill hackers</strong>—smoothing language barriers and providing rudimentary code—not advanced operators seeking new tradecraft. Their impact is marginal compared to early predictions of AI-driven cyber escalation.</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="3-state-operations">3. State Operations</h2>
<h3 id="cyber-reconnaissance-linked-to-kinetic-strikes--cloud-enabled-espionage">Cyber Reconnaissance Linked to Kinetic Strikes &amp; Cloud-Enabled Espionage</h3>
<p>Amazon documented how <strong>Iranian groups</strong>—including <em>Imperial Kitten</em> and <em>MuddyWater</em>—used cyber intrusions to <strong>prepare missile strikes</strong> and assess post-strike damage.<br>
Source: <a href="https://www.darkreading.com/threat-intelligence/iran-exploits-cyber-domain-kinetic-strikes" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer ">Dark Reading</a></p>
<p>Activities included:</p>
<ul>
<li>Tampering with <strong>AIS maritime systems</strong></li>
<li>Accessing <strong>shipboard CCTV</strong></li>
<li>Using <strong>compromised Israeli camera feeds</strong> during strikes on Jerusalem</li>
</ul>
<p>This model—<strong>cyber-enabled kinetic targeting</strong>—collapses reconnaissance and strike cycles into a single operational continuum.</p>
<p><strong>Meanwhile, China’s APT31</strong> conducted prolonged espionage against Russian IT contractors, misusing <strong>OneDrive</strong>, <strong>Dropbox</strong>, <strong>Yandex Cloud</strong>, and even <strong>VirusTotal comments</strong> for covert C2.<br>
Source: <a href="https://www.darkreading.com/cyberattacks-data-breaches/china-spies-russian-it-orgs" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer ">Dark Reading</a></p>
<p>Targeting IT integrators gives indirect access to government systems and critical projects, blurring commercial and strategic intelligence boundaries.</p>
<p>Finally, an Australian national was sentenced to <strong>seven years</strong> for running in-flight <strong>evil-twin Wi-Fi networks</strong>, harvesting credentials and intimate images through fraudulent captive portals.<br>
Source: <a href="https://www.bleepingcomputer.com/news/security/man-behind-in-flight-evil-twin-wifi-attacks-gets-7-years-in-prison" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer ">BleepingComputer</a></p>
<p>The case demonstrates how <strong>everyday digital environments</strong>—airport Wi-Fi, captive portals, travel hotspots—remain viable vectors for credential theft and covert surveillance.</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="implication">Implication</h2>
<p>This week illustrates how threat actors increasingly <strong>corrupt trusted human workflows</strong> rather than exploit technical weaknesses. DPRK weaponises hiring routines; Russian-linked operators act from inside EU borders; Iran and China merge <strong>cyber reconnaissance with state objectives</strong>, using cloud services to mask operations. In parallel, dark LLMs empower novices but do <strong>not</strong> shift the strategic balance of cyber operations.</p>
<p>Leaders should expect more campaigns exploiting ordinary digital interactions—<strong>job applications, cloud tools, travel Wi-Fi</strong>—and a continued trend where <strong>cyber reconnaissance directly shapes physical operations</strong>.</p>
<hr>
]]></description>
</item>
<item>
    <title>How AI Automation Saved 13 Days per UK Civil Servant in 2024</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/2025/how-ai-automation-saved-13-days-per-uk-civil-servant-in-2024/</link>
    <pubDate>Tue, 10 Jun 2025 07:27:09 &#43;0200</pubDate>
    <author>Author</author>
    <guid>http://localhost:1313/2025/how-ai-automation-saved-13-days-per-uk-civil-servant-in-2024/</guid>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>A recent <a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/landmark-government-trial-shows-ai-could-save-civil-servants-nearly-2-weeks-a-year" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer ">UK Government AI experiment</a> revealed that certain tasks can be fully automated, saving up to <strong>13 working days per person annually</strong>.</p>
<p>The results are documented in two reports: <a href="https://www.turing.ac.uk/news/publications/mapping-potential-generative-ai-and-public-sector-work-using-time-use-data" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer "><em>Mapping the Potential</em></a> by the Alan Turing Institute, and The <a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/microsoft-365-copilot-experiment-cross-government-findings-report" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer ">Government Digital Service’s</a> cross-government experiment of <strong>Microsoft 365 Copilot</strong></p>
<p>Between September and December 2024, <strong>20,000 UK civil servants</strong> participated in the trial. The findings identified <strong>four fully automatable activities</strong>:</p>
<ul>
<li>Organising meetings and meeting administration</li>
<li>Creating or updating appointments or bookings</li>
<li>Completing or processing forms</li>
<li>Creating or updating records, databases, or case files</li>
</ul>
<h1 id="key-insights-from-the-experiment">Key Insights from the Experiment</h1>
<ul>
<li><strong>82%</strong> of users expressed a preference not to return to pre-AI workflows.</li>
<li><strong>Time savings</strong> were highest in:
<ul>
<li>Document drafting: <em>up to 24 minutes/day</em></li>
<li>Presentation preparation: <em>19 minutes/day</em></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>On average, <strong>13 working days</strong> were saved per person annually—equivalent to <strong>1,000 working years</strong> saved across all participants (assuming a 260-day working year).</li>
</ul>
<h1 id="economic-implications">Economic Implications</h1>
<p><a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/statistics/civil-service-statistics-2024/statistical-bulletin-civil-service-statistics-2024#:~:text=The%20median%20salary%20in%20the,of%20%c2%a32%2C060%20%286.5%25%29." target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer ">The 2024 median annual salary for a UK civil servant was <strong>£33,980</strong>.</a> For 20,000 staff, the <strong>total annual payroll</strong> equates to:
20,000 × £33,980 = £679,600,000</p>
<p>Assuming a 260-day working year, the <strong>daily cost per civil servant</strong> is:
£33,980 ÷ 260 ≈ £130.69</p>
<p>A 13-day annual saving per person translates to:
13 × £130.69 ≈ £1,699 per person/year</p>
<p>For 20,000 civil servants, the total annual saving is:
20,000 × £1,699 ≈ £33,980,000</p>
<h1 id="some-policy-implications">Some Policy Implications</h1>
<ul>
<li><strong>Reallocation</strong> of budgetary resources to other priority areas</li>
<li><strong>Reskilling</strong> staff for roles where AI still requires a human-in-the-loop</li>
<li><strong>Faster public service delivery</strong>, enabled by freeing up 13 working days per employee</li>
</ul>
<hr>
<p>This AI experiment demonstrates tangible productivity gains but also invites deeper reflection on how public-sector roles might evolve in the years to come.</p>
]]></description>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Revisiting the Letter of Marque</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/2025/revisiting-the-letter-of-marque/</link>
    <pubDate>Sun, 25 May 2025 21:08:05 &#43;0200</pubDate>
    <author>Author</author>
    <guid>http://localhost:1313/2025/revisiting-the-letter-of-marque/</guid>
    <description><![CDATA[<h1 id="revisiting-the-letter-of-marque-leveraging-the-private-sector-in-offensive-cyberspace-operations---an-analytical-reflection-on-historical-analogies-and-contemporary-policy-debates">Revisiting the Letter of Marque: Leveraging the Private Sector in Offensive Cyberspace Operations - <em>An Analytical Reflection on Historical Analogies and Contemporary Policy Debates</em></h1>
<hr>
<h2 id="1-executive-summary">1. Executive Summary</h2>
<p>This policy brief explores a structured model for state-authorized private sector engagement in offensive cyberspace operations. The idea draws inspiration from the historical concept of the letter of marque, which allowed states to authorize private actors to disrupt enemy assets under legal protection. While the 18th-century practice is not directly applicable today, it offers a useful model for assigning limited, accountable roles to private cybersecurity firms in support of national objectives. The brief uses <a href="https://darknetdiaries.com/episode/50/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer ">Operation Glowing Symphony</a>—a coordinated U.S. Cyber Command operation targeting ISIS media infrastructure—as a case study. It demonstrates how state-led offensive operations can be developed, rehearsed, and executed in a way that maintains legal oversight and operational discipline. Rather than opening the domain to unregulated hacking, the exploration focuses on enabling authorized and bounded actions against specific non-state threat actors operating below the threshold of armed conflict.</p>
<p>The model includes time-bound mandates, legal immunity under strict conditions, and mandatory coordination with national agencies. This approach can enhance national resilience and deterrence capacity without expanding permanent state structures. It also offers a practical response to concerns over asymmetric threats from actors with greater scale and coordination than many states can counter alone.</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="2-problem-statement">2. Problem Statement</h2>
<p>States face growing pressure to respond to persistent cyberspace operations conducted by both state and non-state actors. These operations often target critical infrastructure, financial networks, and information systems. Traditional defensive measures, while necessary, have not been sufficient to reduce the frequency or severity of such threats. At the same time, there is a significant gap between national cyber capacity and the capabilities of adversaries. For example, <a href="https://www.nextgov.com/cybersecurity/2025/05/18th-century-war-power-resurfaces-cyber-policy-talks/405526/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer ">according to Nextgov</a>, the U.S. has acknowledged being outnumbered in cybersecurity personnel compared to China by a factor of 50 to 1. In this environment, private sector expertise is both more advanced and more scalable than what is currently available within government structures.</p>
<p>However, no formal framework exists to allow private firms to contribute to offensive operations in a legally sanctioned and coordinated manner. Without such a framework, ad hoc actions risk undermining ongoing intelligence work, triggering diplomatic tensions, or creating legal uncertainties. The absence of an accountable model for private sector participation in offensive cyberspace responses may limit the state&rsquo;s ability to act in grey-zone competition or conflict. A structured, state-authorized mechanism may offer a way to bridge this gap and to guide private action under law, oversight, and clear operational limits.</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="3-background--analogy">3. Background &amp; Analogy</h2>
<p>The concept of a letter of marque originates from maritime law. It was used by states to authorize private vessels to attack and seize enemy ships during wartime. These letters allowed governments to expand their reach without deploying additional naval forces, while also maintaining legal oversight and accountability through courts of admiralty. While this historical mechanism is no longer in use, it offers a useful analogy for structured private participation in offensive cyberspace operations. In both contexts, the state faces a resource gap and must find ways to extend its reach through regulated non-state actors.</p>
<p>In cyber policy discussions, the idea has resurfaced as a metaphor for how private firms might be legally authorized to act against threats such as ransomware groups or transnational cybercriminals. The goal is not to replicate 18th-century practices but to draw lessons about how states can responsibly delegate certain functions under clear legal and operational frameworks. A modern precedent exists in Operation Glowing Symphony (OGS)—a U.S. Cyber Command-led mission to disrupt ISIS’s media operations. OGS was structured, rehearsed, and legally authorized. It demonstrates how a state can conduct offensive cyberspace operations without relying solely on kinetic force or open warfare.</p>
<p>Table 1 illustrates the conceptual similarities between historical maritime practice and this modern cyber operation.</p>
<p><strong>Table 1: Comparison of historical and contemporary State-authorized disruption models</strong></p>
<table>
  <thead>
      <tr>
          <th>Letter of Marque (Historical)</th>
          <th>Operation Glowing Symphony (Modern)</th>
      </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
      <tr>
          <td>Authorized attacks on enemy ships</td>
          <td>Authorized attacks on enemy digital systems</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
          <td>Private actors under state license</td>
          <td>Military cyber teams under joint command</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
          <td>Time- and target-specific</td>
          <td>Scripted, time-bound, legally approved</td>
      </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>
<p>This table supports the brief’s central analogy and highlights the relevance of structured state delegation in contemporary cyber strategy.</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="4-policy-proposal">4. Policy Proposal</h2>
<p>This brief outlines a potential framework that allows vetted private sector actors to carry out time-limited, targeted offensive cyberspace operations under legal oversight. The framework is inspired by historical state practices (letters of marque) and informed by the operational experience of Operation Glowing Symphony.</p>
<p>The model includes the following components:</p>
<p><strong>A. Legal Authorization</strong><br>
Private actors would operate under a formal legal instrument—such as an executive order, legislative provision, or defense authorization. The authorization would define the operation’s scope, time frame, geographic focus, and targets (e.g., non-state threat actors).</p>
<p><strong>B. Eligibility and Oversight</strong><br>
Only pre-vetted private entities—with existing clearances, contractual ties to government, and operational maturity—would qualify. All operations must be pre-approved, monitored, and deconflicted with agencies such as USCYBERCOM, NSA, DHS, or DOJ. Operators must follow rules-of-engagement approved by legal and technical authorities.</p>
<p><strong>C. Operational Limits</strong><br>
All actions must be non-kinetic, focused on disruption or degradation of non-state threat actors&rsquo; digital capabilities. Operations must avoid causing direct, disproportionate, or sustained disruption to civilian services or critical infrastructure not being used for hostile purposes.</p>
<p><strong>D. Legal Protections</strong><br>
Participating firms could receive limited liability protections, akin to those provided under the <a href="https://www.cisa.gov/sites/default/files/publications/Cybersecurity%2520Information%2520Sharing%2520Act%2520of%25202015.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer ">2015 Cybersecurity Information Sharing Act (CISA)</a>, provided their actions comply with formal authorization and oversight requirements. A transparency and review mechanism should be established to monitor outcomes and ensure lawful execution.</p>
<p>Table 2 compares the key attributes of Operation Glowing Symphony with the proposed framework, highlighting how similar principles of authorization, coordination, and legal constraint can be applied to qualified private sector actors in future operations.</p>
<p><strong>Table 2: Comparison between Operation Glowing Symphony and the proposed private-sector offensive cyber framework</strong></p>
<table>
  <thead>
      <tr>
          <th>Feature</th>
          <th>Operation Glowing Symphony</th>
          <th>Proposed Private-Sector Framework</th>
      </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
      <tr>
          <td>Actor Type</td>
          <td>Government cyber teams</td>
          <td>Vetted private contractors</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
          <td>Legal Authority</td>
          <td>Presidential tasking (Task Order 16-0063)</td>
          <td>National statute or executive authorization</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
          <td>Oversight</td>
          <td>Chain of command (JTF-ARES)</td>
          <td>Interagency approval and legal review</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
          <td>Target Focus</td>
          <td>Terrorist media infrastructure</td>
          <td>Non-state threat actors</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
          <td>Coordination</td>
          <td>Full deconfliction across agencies</td>
          <td>Mandatory deconfliction</td>
      </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>
<p>Such a model could help expand national capacity while maintaining legal control and operational discipline.</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="5-addressing-key-concerns">5. Addressing Key Concerns</h2>
<p>The idea of authorizing private actors to conduct offensive cyberspace operations raises valid concerns. These concerns must be addressed through clear legal mandates, operational oversight, and built-in limitations. One concern is that such actions could be misused or lead to escalation. To avoid this, the proposed framework limits operations to non-state targets and requires pre-authorization, coordination, and oversight by national authorities. Actions must also follow strict rules of engagement and remain within legally defined boundaries.</p>
<p>Another concern is the disruption of intelligence collection or interference with military operations. This is addressed through mandatory deconfliction, as demonstrated in Operation Glowing Symphony, where Cyber Command coordinated actions across agencies to avoid operational overlap.</p>
<p>Legal ambiguity is also a common issue. By integrating liability protections and authorization mechanisms similar to existing frameworks (e.g., CISA), this proposal provides a structured legal environment that distinguishes it from unsanctioned so-called &ldquo;hack-back activity.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Finally, the concern that civilian infrastructure could be unintentionally affected is mitigated through the requirement to avoid direct, disproportionate, or sustained disruption to systems not used for hostile purposes.</p>
<p>Table 3 summarizes these concerns alongside the proposed mitigation mechanisms, showing how the framework maintains legal clarity and operational restraint.</p>
<p><strong>Table 3: Key policy concerns and corresponding mitigation measures</strong></p>
<table>
  <thead>
      <tr>
          <th>Concern</th>
          <th>Mitigation Mechanism</th>
      </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
      <tr>
          <td>Escalation or misuse</td>
          <td>Time-limited mandates, strict oversight, non-state targets only</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
          <td>Operational interference</td>
          <td>Interagency deconfliction and legal coordination</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
          <td>Legal uncertainty</td>
          <td>Authorization instruments and liability protections</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
          <td>Civilian infrastructure impact</td>
          <td>Rules of engagement prohibiting disproportionate disruption</td>
      </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>
<p>These measures are designed to help reduce the risk that the framework undermines legal norms or operational stability while supporting state objectives.</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="6-use-case-prioritization">6. Use Case Prioritization</h2>
<p>This framework is not envisioned for use in inter-state armed conflict or against state-controlled military systems. It applies to non-state threat actors operating below the threshold of war, including in active conflict zones, where operations support counterterrorism, counter-crime, or digital stabilization objectives.</p>
<p>Priority targets may include non-state threat actors engaged in disruptive or harmful activities, illicit online platforms, terrorist media outlets disseminating propaganda, and botnet operators undermining essential services. Operations under such a framework could aim to disrupt functionality, seize data, or temporarily deny access to digital infrastructure, while avoiding broader or sustained collateral effects. Table 4 provides examples of eligible and excluded targets, offering a structured approach to prioritization that reflects both legal boundaries and operational discretion. Operations could focus on disruption, data seizure, or temporary denial of digital capabilities, with minimal collateral effects.</p>
<p><strong>Table 4: Target selection parameters for private-sector offensive cyberspace operations</strong></p>
<table>
  <thead>
      <tr>
          <th>Eligible Targets</th>
          <th>Excluded Targets</th>
      </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
      <tr>
          <td>Non-state threat actors engaged in disruptive or harmful activities</td>
          <td>Foreign state-controlled military infrastructure</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
          <td>Terrorist propaganda infrastructure (e.g., ISIS)</td>
          <td>Civilian services not used for hostile purposes</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
          <td>Illicit online platforms</td>
          <td>Platforms in neutral jurisdictions</td>
      </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>
<p>This prioritization supports strategic coherence, aligns with legal boundaries, and maintains operational restraint.</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="7-strategic-benefits">7. Strategic Benefits</h2>
<p>This framework could offer a way to increase national cyber capacity without expanding permanent government structures. By enabling temporary, state-authorized private sector operations, the state can respond more flexibly to time-sensitive threats.</p>
<p>It also supports targeted disruption of adversary networks, which raises operational costs for threat actors and can reduce the frequency or persistence of hostile activity. Importantly, it provides a legal and coordinated alternative to unsanctioned hack-back practices, which risk undermining intelligence efforts and international norms. Table 5 summarizes how the proposed model addresses current limitations in national cyber response capacity, offering structured and lawful enhancements without compromising oversight or strategy.</p>
<p><strong>Table 5: Addressing limitations in current cyber response models</strong></p>
<table>
  <thead>
      <tr>
          <th>Current Limitation</th>
          <th>Benefit of Proposed Framework</th>
      </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
      <tr>
          <td>Limited public capacity to meet emerging threats</td>
          <td>Temporary expansion using vetted private actors</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
          <td>Fragmented or uncoordinated private responses</td>
          <td>Centralized authorization and legal oversight</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
          <td>Inability to impose costs on non-state actors</td>
          <td>Enables proportionate, state-sanctioned disruption</td>
      </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>
<p>The approach supports resilience, burden-sharing, and a more proactive cybersecurity posture.</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="8-recommendations">8. Recommendations</h2>
<p>To explore the viability of this approach, a pilot could be tested through a limited pilot program administered by, for example, either the Department of Defense or the Department of Homeland Security. This pilot could focus on non-state threat actors engaged in disruptive or harmful activities or counter-terrorism operations targeting non-state actors, allowing for the evaluation of legal, technical, and operational procedures in practice.</p>
<p>To support such a pilot, the government could issue a formal legal instrument—either an executive order or a legislative provision—that authorizes time-bound, state-sanctioned offensive cyber activities by designated private entities. Participation could be limited to firms with prior security clearances, demonstrated technical capability, and a history of regulatory compliance.</p>
<p>Oversight must be managed through an interagency review process involving legal, operational, and diplomatic input. This process could be designed to ensure that all activities remain aligned with national law, avoid strategic miscalculation, and support broader policy objectives. These steps can enable a controlled and accountable expansion of national cyber capabilities.</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="9-conclusions">9. Conclusions</h2>
<p>Expanding national cyber capacity through a structured, legally grounded framework for private sector engagement offers a realistic way to address growing operational demands. Drawing on historical analogies and operational lessons, such as Operation Glowing Symphony, the proposal outlines how state-authorized private actions can be integrated into national strategy without undermining legal or strategic norms. By focusing on non-state threats and embedding oversight into every stage, this approach enables measured use of existing expertise while maintaining public accountability. It may represent a step toward more adaptive and coordinated responses to emerging threats in cyberspace.</p>
<p><strong>Disclaimer</strong>: The views expressed in this policy brief are solely those of the author and do not reflect the official positions of any current or past affiliated organizations. All references and case examples are used for illustrative and analytical purposes only.</p>
]]></description>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Safeguarding Innovation</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/2025/safeguarding-innovation/</link>
    <pubDate>Thu, 15 May 2025 08:05:18 &#43;0200</pubDate>
    <author>Author</author>
    <guid>http://localhost:1313/2025/safeguarding-innovation/</guid>
    <description><![CDATA[<p></p>
<p>On 13 May 2025, I had the privilege of joining the event <a href="https://kista.com/events/safeguarding-innovation-in-uncertain-times/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer ">Safeguarding Innovation in Uncertain Times</a> hosted by Kista Science City, where I contributed a keynote address on the theme of organizational resilience in today’s fragmented and hybrid threat landscape.</p>
<p>I argue that the core challenge companies face is structural, cognitive, and naturally, technological. We operate in a world where power is increasingly diffuse, information is often designed to disorient, and decision-making is hindered by the absence of shared structure.</p>
<p>The keynote offered a reflection on how resilience must now be reframed as a capacity to navigate strategic disorder. Drawing on insights from institutional theory and cyber practice, I argued that resilience requires more than technical security controls. It demands institutional thinking, cognitive clarity, and deliberate routines that stabilize expectations even in rapidly changing environments.</p>
<p>In the absence of hegemonic order—whether in geopolitics or within markets—structure must emerge from norms, shared awareness, and operational coherence. That task increasingly falls to firms themselves.</p>
<p>The invitation to speak at this event underscored that the private sector is a principal arena for shaping the norms, practices, and collaborative structures needed to build resilience in today’s global (in)security environment.</p>
<p><em>If your institution is navigating similar questions, I welcome further dialogue.</em></p>
]]></description>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Rapid, Affordable AI: Transforming Cost, Speed, and Strategic Capability</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/2025/rapid-affordable-ai-transforming-cost-speed-and-strategic-capability/</link>
    <pubDate>Sun, 16 Feb 2025 21:30:25 &#43;0100</pubDate>
    <author>Author</author>
    <guid>http://localhost:1313/2025/rapid-affordable-ai-transforming-cost-speed-and-strategic-capability/</guid>
    <description><![CDATA[<p></p>
<p>Artificial intelligence is advancing at an unprecedented pace. A 2019 <a href="https://www.computerweekly.com/news/252475371/Stanford-University-finds-that-AI-is-outpacing-Moores-Law" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer ">report</a> by Stanford, McKinsey &amp; Company, Google, PwC, OpenAI, and others revealed that while AI performance once doubled roughly every two years—consistent with Moore’s Law—since 2012, <a href="https://www.computerweekly.com/news/252475371/Stanford-University-finds-that-AI-is-outpacing-Moores-Law" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer ">compute has been doubling every 3.4 months</a>. This dramatic acceleration is evident not only in the frequent rollout of new models by tech giants but also in the emergence of innovative competitors.</p>
<p>This rapid advancement continues. Recent reports have highlighted a breakthrough: a state-of-the-art reasoning model, whose performance rivals OpenAI’s O1, was developed for <a href="https://mashable.com/article/openai-o1-reasoning-model-rival-less-than-50-dollars" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer ">less than $50 and was trained in just 26 minutes</a>. Researchers achieved these cost reductions through a novel approach detailed in a recent <a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/2501.19393" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer ">arXiv preprint</a>. Instead of overhauling existing architectures, their method optimizes the way AI models process information at the moment of use—effectively unlocking and scaling the inherent reasoning capabilities of large pretrained models while slashing computational demands.</p>
<p>Adding further momentum to this trend is <a href="https://novasky-ai.github.io/posts/sky-t1/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer ">Novasky AI’s new Sky-T1 model</a>. According to the company, Sky-T1 combines innovative training techniques with streamlined architectures to deliver scalable, on-demand reasoning capabilities at a remarkably low cost. Together, these advancements underscore a paradigm shift: affordable, fast-to-deploy, and high-performance AI is now within reach.</p>
<p>Yet, as with any disruptive technology, these breakthroughs present a double-edged sword. While they promise to revolutionize sectors ranging from cybersecurity to financial services by making sophisticated AI tools accessible to a broader range of users, they also raise critical security concerns. The same low-cost, high-performance systems could be exploited by threat actors enhancing their operational capabilities.</p>
<p>For policymakers and security strategists, this accelerating evolution in AI calls for a dual approach. On one hand, regulatory policies must be developed to mitigate misuse and protecting against emerging threats. On the other, strategic investments in innovative AI for deterrence and defense are essential to counterbalance adversarial capabilities.</p>
]]></description>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Policy Implications of State-backed APTs’ Use of AI in Cyberspace</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/2025/policy-implications-of-state-backed-apts-use-of-ai-in-cyberspace/</link>
    <pubDate>Mon, 03 Feb 2025 12:24:05 &#43;0100</pubDate>
    <author>Author</author>
    <guid>http://localhost:1313/2025/policy-implications-of-state-backed-apts-use-of-ai-in-cyberspace/</guid>
    <description><![CDATA[<p></p>
<p>Recent confirmations by Google and OpenAI reveal that state-backed APT groups are increasingly employing AI tools—such as Gemini and ChatGPT—to expedite reconnaissance, malware development, and influence operations. AI-tools have the capabilities to <a href="https://www.scworld.com/news/googles-big-sleep-llm-agent-discovers-exploitable-bug-in-sqlite" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer ">discover zero-days</a>.</p>
<p>Current evidence indicates that several <a href="https://www.bleepingcomputer.com/news/security/google-says-hackers-abuse-gemini-ai-to-empower-their-attacks/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer ">state-sponsored APT groups</a> utilize AI-tools to enhance cyber espionage, phishing, and <a href="https://www.bleepingcomputer.com/news/security/openai-confirms-threat-actors-use-chatgpt-to-write-malware/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer ">influence campaigns</a>. Certain threat actors are reportedly employing generative AI for targeted reconnaissance on critical installations, scripting automated attacks, and establishing persistent post-compromise footholds. Similarly, some groups have been observed fabricating job applications to infiltrate organizations under false identities. In contrast, other adversaries, while exploring AI-enhanced malware modification and encryption techniques, appear to engage less with externally developed AI tools—likely due to heightened operational security considerations.</p>
<p>These trends underscore two critical implications. First, the integration of AI in cyberspace operations reduces the necessity for advanced coding skills, thereby lowering the technical threshold for adversaries and enabling rapid adaptation of malware. Second, the ongoing challenges of jailbreaking AI models—demonstrated in security assessments of certain systems—pose significant risks that warrant immediate attention.</p>
<p>Threat actors seeking to exploit AI tools to advance their strategic objectives should not come as a surprise to policymakers or technology leaders. While AI tools are likely to increase both the pace and sophistication of cyberattacks, it is imperative for policymakers to recognize that the rapid pace of technological change is compressing policy lifespans. Whereas policies once spanned five or ten years, today’s interconnected and AI-driven environment may require revisions every three years—or even more frequently.</p>
<p>The proactive threat intelligence sharing undertaken by companies such as Google and OpenAI represents a crucial first step toward situational awareness. By rapidly identifying and disclosing emerging threats, these initiatives inform more agile policy responses. This approach is essential where the window for effective policy intervention is shrinking, and traditional long-term policy frameworks may no longer suffice.</p>
<p>Photo by Midjourney.</p>
]]></description>
</item>
<item>
    <title>A Sputnik Moment in AI?</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/2025/a-sputnik-moment-in-ai/</link>
    <pubDate>Sun, 02 Feb 2025 17:57:01 &#43;0100</pubDate>
    <author>Author</author>
    <guid>http://localhost:1313/2025/a-sputnik-moment-in-ai/</guid>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>Recent debates have focused on whether DeepSeek’s achievement in generating a new model with comparatively limited resources qualifies as a “Sputnik moment” for Western AI companies. This discussion requires distinguishing between developing an entirely new model and adapting pre-existing models. DeepSeek’s approach exemplifies the latter; their methodology involves refining established large language models rather than constructing a new system from scratch.</p>
<p></p>
<p>DeepSeek asserts that its models are “distilled from DeepSeek-R1” and “based on Llama and Qwen” (as seen in the above screenshot, taken from <a href="https://ollama.com/library/deepseek-r1" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer ">here</a>). In this context, “distilled” refers to the process of transferring the reasoning patterns from a larger, complex <a href="https://www.datacamp.com/blog/distillation-llm" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer ">&ldquo;teacher&rdquo; model to a smaller &ldquo;student&rdquo; model</a>. Given that Llama and Qwen were originally developed by Meta and Alibaba Cloud respectively, the adaptation process employed by DeepSeek requires fewer resources than building an entirely new model: a task typically associated with large technology companies.</p>
<p>If DeepSeek had developed an entirely new model, the achievement would align with current achievements and would not necessarily represent a breakthrough. However, by developing a new model, based on existing models and distilled from a third model, this may be a &ldquo;Sputnik moment.&rdquo; Microsoft&rsquo;s CEO Satya Nadella commented that DeepSeek <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/technology/2025/01/30/deepseek-microsoft-meta-investors/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer ">“has had some real innovations”</a>.</p>
<p>Further empirical analysis is required as additional technical details emerge, particularly from independent investigations by entities such as researchers at <a href="https://huggingface.co/blog/open-r1" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer ">Hugging Face</a>.</p>
<p>This case illustrates that organizations can, through adaptation and distillation, develop specialized models optimized for targeted applications at a fraction of the cost of larger, more complex models.</p>
]]></description>
</item>
<item>
    <title>How do cyber threats impact Canada’s national security, economy, and society?</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/2024/how-do-cyber-threats-impact-canadas-national-security-economy-and-society/</link>
    <pubDate>Thu, 31 Oct 2024 10:30:37 &#43;0200</pubDate>
    <author>Author</author>
    <guid>http://localhost:1313/2024/how-do-cyber-threats-impact-canadas-national-security-economy-and-society/</guid>
    <description><![CDATA[<p></p>
<p><em>The figure shows the state cyber program ecosystem to &ldquo;support or perform cyber threat activities.&rdquo; (Source: CCCS, 2024 p. 10)</em></p>
<p>The full report is available at the <a href="https://www.cyber.gc.ca/sites/default/files/national-cyber-threat-assessment-2025-2026-e.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer ">Canadian Centre for Cyber Security</a>.</p>
<hr>
<p>Canada’s <em>National Cyber Threat Assessment 2025–2026</em> by the Canadian Centre for Cyber Security (CCCS), part of the Communications Security Establishment (CSE), brings forward an urgent question: <strong>How do cyber threats impact Canada’s national security, economy, and society?</strong> By examining the range of state and non-state cyber actors, emerging trends, and strategic vulnerabilities, the report provides insights for understanding Canada’s cyber challenges.</p>
<p>The CCCS identifies multiple state-sponsored actors using cyberspace operations to further political and economic agendas. <strong>China</strong> stands out as the most advanced adversary, targeting Canadian institutions for espionage, IP theft, and influence operations. <strong>Russia</strong> focuses on destabilization efforts through influence campaigns, while <strong>Iran and North Korea</strong> engage in cybercrime and ransomware to fund state agendas and control opposition. Meanwhile, <strong>India’s</strong> activities increasingly reflect diplomatic tensions with Canada, as its cyber capabilities expand.</p>
<p>The report also highlights cybercrime’s evolving landscape, especially <strong>ransomware</strong>, which remains a significant threat to Canada’s critical infrastructure. The growth of <strong>Cybercrime-as-a-Service (CaaS)</strong> facilitates attacks by allowing less-skilled actors to leverage advanced tools, significantly impacting healthcare, energy, and government services.</p>
<h3 id="emerging-trends-and-recommended-solutions">Emerging Trends and Recommended Solutions</h3>
<p>Emergent trends such as <strong>AI-driven threats</strong> are reshaping this landscape. AI enables precision in phishing and social engineering, boosting the volume and personalization of attacks. Moreover, as cyber actors increasingly target <strong>edge devices</strong> and exploit <strong>domestic infrastructure</strong>, evasion becomes easier, challenging traditional defense mechanisms. <strong>Vendor concentration</strong> amplifies vulnerabilities, and <strong>dual-use technologies</strong> used by both civilian and military sectors, like <em>satellite communications</em>, are becoming high-priority targets for state-sponsored attacks.</p>
<p>In response, the CCCS calls for a robust strategy to build Canada’s resilience. Strengthened <em>intelligence-sharing</em>, both nationally and with <strong>Five Eyes allies</strong>, would help monitor and counteract these threats. The report also recommends intensified cybercrime enforcement, especially to disrupt ransomware and CaaS operations, and emphasizes investing in advanced detection technology to stay ahead of evolving tactics. Importantly, <strong>accountability from dominant tech providers</strong> is necessary to mitigate systemic risks, reinforcing the resilience of Canada’s digital ecosystem.</p>
<p>Implementing these solutions could significantly impact Canadian infrastructure, making essential services such as healthcare, transportation, and energy more resilient. It would also reinforce collaboration with the private sector, creating a more proactive cybersecurity posture across industries. A stronger defense against ransomware could stabilize the economy by reducing ransom payments and recovery costs for businesses and public institutions. Furthermore, bolstered cybersecurity would elevate Canada’s global standing, positioning it as a proactive and resilient cyber nation.</p>
<p>The <a href="https://www.cyber.gc.ca/sites/default/files/national-cyber-threat-assessment-2025-2026-e.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer ">National Cyber Threat Assessment 2025–2026</a> underscores the need for Canada to adopt a collaborative, technology-driven approach to cybersecurity. Strengthening defenses, investing in advanced tools, and fostering alliances are all essential for safeguarding Canadian citizens, economy, and national security. The report ultimately reflects Canada’s commitment to becoming a leader in cybersecurity resilience, aligning its efforts with global allies to tackle an increasingly complex cyber threat landscape.</p>
]]></description>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Nytt NCSC</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/2024/nytt-ncsc/</link>
    <pubDate>Sat, 20 Apr 2024 15:30:37 &#43;0200</pubDate>
    <author>Author</author>
    <guid>http://localhost:1313/2024/nytt-ncsc/</guid>
    <description><![CDATA[<p></p>
<p>Utredningen återfinns på <a href="https://www.regeringen.se/rattsliga-dokument/departementsserien-och-promemorior/2024/04/ett-nytt-nationellt-cybersakerhetscenter/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer ">Regeringskansliets hemsida</a>.</p>
<h2 id="uppdraget-är-slutfört-utredaren-har-överlämnat-delbetänkandet-ett-nytt-nationellt-cybersäkerhetscenter--ändamålsenliga-och-effektiva-former-för-ledning-organisering-och-styrning">Uppdraget är slutfört. Utredaren har överlämnat delbetänkandet &ldquo;Ett nytt Nationellt cybersäkerhetscenter – Ändamålsenliga och effektiva former för ledning, organisering och styrning&rdquo;.</h2>
<p>Vad betyder detta för NCSC, näringslivet, samhället i stort och Sverige?</p>
<p>Nedan ger jag mina tankar som baseras på utredningens innehåll. Först beskriver jag de utmaningar som NCSC stod inför. I nästa steg presenterar jag de lösningar som rapporten rekommenderar. Därefter utforskar jag vad dessa förändringar kan innebära för näringslivet, samhället i stort, och Sverige. Slutligen reflekterar jag över den bredare betydelsen för det svenska samhället och Sverige i stort.</p>
<h3 id="möjliga-utmaningar-som-ncsc-stod-inför">Möjliga utmaningar som NCSC stod inför:</h3>
<p><strong>Ledningsstruktur</strong>: NCSC behöver en tydlig och effektiv ledningsstruktur för att hantera cyberhot och IT-incidenter.</p>
<p><strong>Myndighetssamverkan</strong>: Det krävs en förbättrad samverkan mellan de sju myndigheter som ingår i NCSC.</p>
<p><strong>Privat-offentlig samverkan</strong>: NCSC måste utveckla sin roll som nationell plattform för samverkan mellan privata och offentliga aktörer för att effektivt hantera informations- och cybersäkerhetfrågor.</p>
<p><strong>Internationella samarbeten</strong>: NCSC behöver stärka sina internationella samarbeten för att effektivt kunna hantera gränsöverskridande cyberhot och IT-incidenter. Detta inkluderar att vara en samlad kontaktpunkt för internationella frågor inom cybersäkerhet.</p>
<h3 id="utredningen-rekommenderar-följande-lösningar">Utredningen rekommenderar följande lösningar:</h3>
<p><strong>Förordningsreglerad ledning</strong>: Förslaget innebär att Försvarets radioanstalt ska ha huvudansvaret för att leda samordning, utveckling och genomförande av NCSC:s verksamhet. Det bör betonas att NCSC får tämligen stor autonomi med en egen regeringsutsedd chef och en egen förordning vid sidan av FRA:s samt att ansvar för upplägget av den inre verksamheten.</p>
<p><strong>MPF som centermyndighet</strong>: Det finns ömsesidiga fördelar med en nära operativ samverkan mellan MPF och NCSC. Sådan samverkan kan bland annat bestå i utbyte av information och bedömningar i syfte att skapa lägesuppfattningar rörande allvarliga antagonistiska hot mot Sverige.</p>
<p><strong>Myndighetssamverkan</strong>: Varje centermyndighets skyldighet att medverka i och bidra till NCSC:s verksamhet inom ramen för sitt verksamhetsområde ska framgå av respektive myndighets instruktion.</p>
<p><strong>Operativ verksamhetsorganisation</strong>: Den operativa verksamhetens organisation ska inte regleras i förordning utan byggas upp utifrån NCSC:s behov. Centret bör utarbeta och bestämma lämpliga former för operativ samverkan och deconfliction.</p>
<p><strong>Överföring av CSIRT-funktionen CERT-SE</strong>: Effektivt utförande av NCSC:s uppgifter förutsätter att verksamheten i den nationella CSIRT:en (Computer Emergency Response Team) förs över från Myndigheten för samhällsskydd och beredskap (MSB) till Försvarets radioanstalt och NCSC. De närmare förutsättningarna för denna verksamhetsöverföring bör utredas i ett annat sammanhang. Försvarets radioanstalt och MSB bör under tiden genomföra en så nära integration av verksamheterna som möjligt.</p>
<h3 id="vad-kan-detta-innebära-för-näringslivet-samhället-i-stort-och-sverige">Vad kan detta innebära för näringslivet, samhället i stort, och Sverige?</h3>
<p><strong>Stärkt cybersäkerhet</strong>: Förslagen syftar till att höja Sveriges förmåga att förebygga, upptäcka och hantera cyberhot och IT-incidenter, vilket är avgörande för nationell säkerhet.</p>
<p><strong>Samordnad insats</strong>: Genom att centralisera ledningen och samordna myndigheternas insatser inom NCSC, kan effektiviteten i att hantera cyberhot öka.</p>
<p><strong>Näringslivets roll</strong>: Näringslivet och andra offentliga aktörer kommer att vara en viktig del i samverkan med NCSC, vilket kan leda till bättre skydd mot cyberattacker för både privata och offentliga sektorer.</p>
<p><strong>Internationellt samarbete</strong>: NCSC kommer att koordinera internationella samarbeten relaterade till cybersäkerhet, vilket kan stärka Sveriges position och bidra till globala cybersäkerhet.</p>
<h3 id="reflektioner-över-den-bredare-betydelsen-för-ncsc-näringslivet-samhället-i-stort-och-sverige">Reflektioner över den bredare betydelsen för NCSC, näringslivet, samhället i stort och Sverige.</h3>
<p>Den föreslagna omstruktureringen av det Nationella cybersäkerhetscentret (NCSC) syftar till att centralisera ledningen av cybersäkerhetsinsatserna i Sverige. Denna centralisering är avsedd att stärka landets förmåga att effektivt hantera cyberhot och IT-incidenter. Genom att etablera en mer centraliserad ledning och styrning förväntas Sverige uppnå snabbare respons och mer effektiv samordning vid hantering av cyberattacker, vilket är kritiskt för nationens säkerhet och operativa beredskap.</p>
<p>Näringslivets roll kan komma att öka med NCSC som en plattform för privat-offentlig samverkan. Det är troligt att näringslivet kommer att få bättre stöd och rådgivning kring cybersäkerhet. NCSC kan också, i samarbete med privata aktörer, snabbt koordinera en nätverksbaserad respons till cyberhot (enligt devisen &ldquo;det krävs nätverk för att skydda nätverk&rdquo;). Detta kan bidra till ökad motståndskraft mot cyberattacker, stärka förtroendet för den digitala infrastrukturen, och säkra ekonomisk säkerhet.</p>
<p>Samhället blir säkrare när medborgare och offentliga tjänster skyddas mot cyberhot, tack vare att cybersäkerheten stärks på nationell nivå. Detta kan även främja innovation och digital tillväxt i Sverige, och göra riket mer konkurrenskraftigt globalt.</p>
<p>Sveriges ställning inom internationell cybersäkerhet och det förebyggande arbetet mot cyberhot stärks av ett nytt NCSC. Detta kan även leda till djupare internationella samarbeten och ökat kunskapsutbyte.</p>
<h3 id="stärkt-svensk-cybersäkerhet">Stärkt svensk cybersäkerhet</h3>
<p>Sammanfattningsvis kan man säga att den föreslagna centraliseringen av det Nationella cybersäkerhetscentret (NCSC) under Försvarets radioanstalt syftar till att stärka Sveriges förmåga att hantera cyberhot och IT-incidenter mer effektivt. NCSC får tämligen stor autonomi med en egen regeringsutsedd chef och en egen förordning vid sidan av FRA:s samt att ansvar för upplägget av den inre verksamheten. Genom att optimera samordningen och responstiden vid cyberattacker, inte bara förbättras näringslivets och det offentliga sektorns cybersäkerhet, utan även det allmänna förtroendet för den digitala infrastrukturen stärks, och cyberekonomisk säkerhet säkras. Denna omstrukturering förväntas också bidra till ett säkrare samhälle, främja nationell digital innovation och tillväxt samt förbättra Sveriges konkurrenskraft och position i internationella cybersäkerhetdiskussioner, vilket möjliggör djupare internationella samarbeten och kunskapsutbyte.</p>
]]></description>
</item>
<item>
    <title>There is no clear cybersecurity policy</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/2024/there-is-no-clear-cybersecurity-policy/</link>
    <pubDate>Wed, 28 Feb 2024 14:14:02 &#43;0100</pubDate>
    <author>Author</author>
    <guid>http://localhost:1313/2024/there-is-no-clear-cybersecurity-policy/</guid>
    <description><![CDATA[<p></p>
<p>This is a translated English version of the original, which is in Swedish at <a href="https://www.di.se/debatt/det-saknas-en-tydlig-cybersakerhetspolicy/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreffer ">DI Debatt</a>.</p>
<h3 id="sweden-needs-a-cyber-deterrence-strategy-and-together-with-national-and-international-partners-conduct-offensive-cyber-operations-against-threat-actors">Sweden needs a cyber deterrence strategy and, together with national and international partners, conduct offensive cyber operations against threat actors</h3>
<p>A clear Swedish cybersecurity policy is important for deterring cyber threats and showing that attacks have consequences. Examples of a well-designed deterrence strategy can be found in the US, the EU and Australia. In light of the recent ransomware attack that affected more than 120 authorities and businesses, this should also be considered for Sweden.</p>
<p>The ransomware attacks against Coop, Kalix municipality, the Church of Sweden and TietoEvry highlight the urgent need to deter cyber threats. The attacks have had a significant impact on Swedes&rsquo; daily lives, economic interests and, by extension, Swedish security. The situation emphasises the importance of Swedish policies that increase the costs and risks for threat actors and make it clear that it does not pay to attack Swedish interests.</p>
<p>Bill 2020/21:30 discusses the need to strengthen cyber defence capabilities, both defensively and offensively. The focus on deterring cyber threats is limited. The Defence Committee&rsquo;s report &ldquo;Kraftsamling&rdquo; deals with deterrence for security in the Euro-Atlantic area, including Sweden&rsquo;s role in NATO, but not Sweden&rsquo;s own cyber deterrence.</p>
<p>What can be done? To deal with cyber threats, such as ransomware attacks, we should understand that Swedish interests are under continuous attack over time, and Sweden is constantly dealing with threats in cyberspace. This emphasises the importance of cyber deterrence, as illustrated by the 2014 Sony hack and the Colonial Pipeline attack.</p>
<p><strong>The cyber attack on Sony Pictures</strong>, triggered by the film &lsquo;The Interview&rsquo; and its fictional plot against the North Korean leader, led to international controversy and questions about US cyber deterrence. Admiral Michael S. Rogers of the US Cyber Command emphasised the global impact of the attack. In response, the US government under President Obama developed a new cyber security policy and sanctions against individuals involved in cyber attacks, which was an important step in addressing cyber threats.</p>
<p><strong>The Colonial Pipeline case</strong>, a major ransomware attack, led to fuel shortages, price increases and panic buying in the US. The US launched a comprehensive government effort to restore operations and mitigate the impact on the energy sector and the public. General Paul Nakasone of the US Cyber Command emphasised the strategic importance of the attack and the coordinated response of the Cyber National Mission Force and other government agencies and international partners to combat such threats.</p>
<p><strong>International cooperation is essential</strong> to tackle cyber threats. Many countries face the challenge of identifying and acting against threat actors, but cooperation has proven effective in imposing sanctions. For example, negotiations between the US and Russia led to the arrest of an individual behind the Colonial Pipeline attack after months of dialogue.</p>
<p><strong>The EU has imposed sanctions</strong> on those responsible for cyber attacks such as &lsquo;WannaCry&rsquo; and &lsquo;NotPetya&rsquo;, including travel bans and asset freezes. ENISA, the EU&rsquo;s cybersecurity agency, and Europol&rsquo;s EC3, which fights cybercrime, play an important role in helping member states improve their ability to deal with cyber threats, contributing to a stronger common front against cyber attacks.</p>
<p><strong>Australia has imposed sanctions</strong> on a Russian following an international investigation involving the FBI, NSA and GCHQ for a cyber attack on &ldquo;Medibank Private&rdquo;. General Nakasone emphasises &ldquo;integrated deterrence&rdquo; as a strategy, meaning coordination of offensive cyber operations and collaboration across different arenas and partners, which is important in a world of continuous geopolitical competition.</p>
<p>Based on the above, the following lessons emerge:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>Cyber deterrence requires a society-wide cyber strategy and responsibility from decision-makers, where offensive cyber operations can also be undertaken with the support of extended legal authority and international jurisdiction. With this support, the Swedish Armed Forces, in collaboration with the FRA, key companies and partners, can conduct offensive cyber operations against identified threat actors. These could include disabling infrastructure, securing Bitcoin or changing email passwords. Effective intelligence is essential to uncover the identities of the attackers.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>The strategy should clearly state that ransomware attacks are a strategic threat to Sweden: all attacks will be responded to decisively, in cooperation with international partners.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Ransomware attacks threaten the Swedish economy and security and must be managed seamlessly during all phases of peace, crisis and war.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Gazmend Huskaj</strong> is Head of Cyber Security at the Geneva Centre for Security Policy (GCSP), previously a doctoral student in offensive cyberspace operations at the Swedish Defence University and Director of Intelligence in cyber-related issues in the Swedish Armed Forces.</p>
]]></description>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
